Register of the Roy Pateman papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Roy Pateman papers
1954-2016
2016C22
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes, 1 card file box (2.5 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, printed matter, photographs, videorecordings, and sound recordings relating mainly to political conditions in Eritrea and the history of Eritrea.
Pateman, Roy.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2016.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Roy Pateman, a British political scientist, was born in England on August 15, 1935. After receiving his Bachelor of Science from the University of Nottingham in 1958, he continued his graduate studies at London and Reading Universities, graduating in 1967 and 1971, respectively. He was also a counter-intelligence operative of the British Army in Kenya and the United Kingdom from 1958 to 1965.
Pateman is Professor Emeritus of Political Science at the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA), after many years of teaching, research, and administrative experience at Princeton University; University of Sydney, Australia; University of California, Los Angeles; the Hoover Institution; and the University of Asmara, Eritrea.
Pateman spent twenty-five years working voluntarily for the Eritrean Relief Association (ERA) in Australia, Sweden, the US, the UK, Eritrea, and Sudan. He also has considerable experience working with the media, television, and radio broadcasting in the United States, Great Britain, Australia, and Eritrea.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Roy Pateman papers document forty-seven years of Pateman's professional career, from 1954 through 2016. The collection includes correspondence, notes, reports, pamphlets, transcriptions of radio broadcasts relating to Africa, syllabi, other printed matter, photographs, videorecordings, and sound recordings relating mainly to political conditions in Eritrea and the history of Eritrea.
Eritrea--History.; Eritrea--Politics and government.; Video tapes.; Audiotapes.
- Biographical File, 2016 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains Pateman's curriculum vitae.
- Office File, 2016 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  List of materials donated to the Hoover Institution.
- Speeches and Writings, 1971-2009 (Boxes 1-2)
  - "The Afar Question," typed essay, Stanford University, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - "African Marxists," typed essay, faculty seminar, 1986 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Articles, 1979-2008 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Book reviews of Eritrea: Even the Stones Are Still Burning by Roy Pateman, 1991-1998
    - De Waal, Alex, 1992 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Killion, Tom, 1992 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Romandini, Massimo, 1998 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Tekle, Amare, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Book reviews by Roy Pateman, 1976-2009
    - Angola's Last Best Chance for Peace, Paul Hare, 1999 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - Anatomy: Flexible Solution to Ethnic Conflicts, Ruth Lapidoth, 1999 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Catch 22, Joseph Heller, 1976 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Crisis and Terror in the Horn of Africa, Pietro Toggia, 2002 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Cry, the Beloved Country, Alan Paton, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Elections and Conflict Management in Africa, Timothy D. Sisk and Andrew Reynolds, 2001 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Language and Education in Eritrea: A Case Study of Language, Diversity, Policy and Practice, Chefena Hailemariam, 2002 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Military Withdrawal from Politics: A Comparative Study, Talukder Maniruzzaman, 1983 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Nations, Identities, Cultures, V. Y. Mudimbe, 1996 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Nations without States: A Historical Dictionary of Contemporary National Movements, James Minahan, 1997 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Nuclear Power, Walter Patterson, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 20)
    - The Political Economy of Ethiopia, Marina Ottaway, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 21)
    - Soldiers, Martyrs, Traitors and the Eritrean Exile in Eritrea and Diaspora, Tricia Redeker Hepner, 2009 (Box-folder 1: 22)
    - Towards Asmara: An African Novel, Thomas Keneally, 1990 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - "Discovering the Eritrean Liberation Movement (ELM)," typed essay based on a lecture presented at the University of Asmara, 1998 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Discussion Course 446, University of California Los Angeles (UCLA) and University of Sydney, Australia, 1980s-1990s (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Discussion group course, University of Sidney, undated (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Discussion notes based on "Ulster," published in the Sunday Times, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Eritrea, undated (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Eritrea report talks, during semester at the University of Asmara, 1997 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Eritrean Relief Committee (ERC) fundraising keynote speech, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Interview transcripts with Issayas Afeworki, 1985-1987
    - Engevik, Ove, 1985 (Box-folder 1: 31)
    - Pateman, Roy, 1987 (Box-folder 1: 32)
    - Streicher, 1987 (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - Israel, Ethiopia, and Eritrea, 1987 (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Notes about sound recordings, Eritrean tapes, 1983-1991 (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - Opening address to the Liberation Conference, Sydney, Australia, 1981 (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - Program flyers and agendas, 1976-2000 (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - Politics 2, syllabus, University of Sydney, Australia, 1982 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Radio programs, notes and transcripts, Sydney, Australia
    - Africa Today, various topics, 1978-1987 (Box-folder 2: 2-4)
    - Sundry Talks, discussion on the Vietnam War, Asmara, Eritrea, 2000 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Sydney Breakfast Show, various topics, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - "Revolution and Agrarian Reform in Ethiopia," book review by Roy Pateman of Agrarian Reform in Ethiopia, Dessalegn Rahmato, 1986 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - "Revolution, Ras Tafari and Reggae--The New Politics of the West Indies," Canberra, Australia, 1980 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - "Self Determination: The Referendum in Eritrea and Western Sahara and Their Implications for Democracy,", 1993 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - "Some Implications of Military Cooperation between Two Pariah States," Melbourne, Australia, 1980 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - "The Structure and Function of the Eritrean Government,", 1997 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Syllabus, Department of Political Science, UCLA, 1996 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Talk at the University of Asmara, Eritrea, 2000 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Talk at the University of South Wales: Forum on 45 Years of Terror, 1982 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - "Talk to Tension Areas," class, UCLA, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - "Trading Claims: Deportations in the Horn of Africa," African Studies Centre, University of California, Berkeley, 2000 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Various topics. Eritrea, 1983-2000 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - "Zimbabwe: Economic, Political and Social Development since Independence," Australia, 1980 (Box-folder 2: 18)
- Correspondence, 1980-2000 (Box 2)
  - Burress, Richard T., 1984 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Campgnoli, Duccio, 1989 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Eritrean Studies Association (ESA), circa 1990 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Eritrean People’s Liberation Front (EPLF), Secretariat, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Fesshatzion, Tekie, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Greenfield, Richard, 2000 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - McNeill, Ian, 1982 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Otayek, R., 1991 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Referendum Commission of Eritrea (RCE), 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Rudner, Martin, 1980 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Wolde-ab, Yisak, 1997 (Box-folder 2: 29)
- Subject File, 1954-2005 (Box 2-32)
  - "Address to the Nation by Provisional Government of Eritrea (PGE) Secretary General, Mr. Issaias Afewerki on the Outcome of the Referendum,", 1993 April 27 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - "Afar Customary Law," Jamaluddin A. Redo, 1971 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - African Studies Association of Australia and the Pacific Newsletter, Vol. I, No. 1, 1989 (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - Anniversary (1st) of Eritrea’s Liberation Program, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - "Clarification on the Misconceptions about the Referendum,", 1991 October 16 (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - Community courts and penal codes, 1998, 2005 (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - Eritrean Relief Committee (ERC) (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - "Eritrea Self-Governing" by E. R. J. Hussey, African Affairs, 1954 (Box-folder 2: 37)
  - Eritrean Studies Association (ESA) Newsletter, 1996-2000 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Eritreana, 1991 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - "Finding Space for Muslim Personal Law in Eritrea,", 2001 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - "Islamic Court Records: A Survey for the Social and Economic History of Massawa in the 19th Century," Jonathan Miran, 2001 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - "La Lumière sur l’Institut Al Azhar: Une Publication de la Direction Générale de l’Institut Al Azhar,", 2001 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - "Liberation and Democratization in Africa,", 1993 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - "The People’s Democratic Republic of Ethiopia: Masking and Unmasking Tragedy,", 1991 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Referendum Commission of Eritrea (RCE), 1993
    - Code of Conduct, 1993 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Guideline for Rolling Stations, 1993 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Monitor Elections Day: Checklist, 1993 (Box-folder 3: 10)
- Printed Matter, 1983-2011 (Box 3-5)
  - Africa Today: Scholarly Views of Ethiopia’s Political Economy in the 1980s, 1991 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Blood, Land and Sex: A Journey into Eritrean Legal and Political Pluralism, 2002 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Calendar, Eritrean People’s Liberation Front (EPLF), Eritrea, 1991 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Case Studies of Regional Conflicts and Conflict Resolutions, 1989 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Disaster and Development of the Horn of Africa, 1995 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - "Eritrea: An Emerging New Nation in the Troubled Horn?,", 1991 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Eritrea in Relief, 1986 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - The Eritrean Durrah Odyssey, 1983 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Horn of Africa, Vol. XIII, Nos. 3 and 4, Vol. XIV, Nos. 1 and 2, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Journal of Eritrean Studies, Vol. III, No. 2, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - The Long Struggle for Eritrea: For Independence and Constructive Peace, 1988 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Newspapers and magazine articles by Roy Pateman, 1984-2004 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Sangue, Terra E Sesso, Lyda Favali and Roy Pateman, 2003 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Student Selection and Retention at the University of Asmara, Eritrea, 2004 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - The Sworn Virgin: Albania, 2011 (Box-folder 5: 2)
- Photographs, 1992-2004 (Box 5)
  - Eritrea I-IV, undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Miscellaneous I and II, 1998-2004 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Pictures from the war front I-III, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Pictures from the war front I and II, countryside III and IV, 2000 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Picture slides, first anniversary of Eritrean independence, 1992 (Box-folder 5: 7)
- Sound Recordings, 1983-1993 (Box 6)
  Sound recordings include two-sided tapes capturing Roy Pateman's work in Eritrea.
  - 1983
    - Tape 1, August 1-23 (Box 6)
      Side A:
      Airport sounds and arrival in Acropole Hotel, Dubai. In Arabic and English.
      Interview in Khartoum with Issayas Afeworki, Vice Secretary General of the Eritrean People’s Liberation Front, on general principles and policy.
      Interview with Gebre Michael Mengistu, Secretary of the Eritrean Relief Association.
      Side B:
      Eritrean Relief Association clinic in Port Sudan.
      Tour with Negussie, medical director, and Fassic of the Eritrean Relief Association clinic in Khartoum.
    - Tape 2, August 23-27 (Box 6)
      Land cruiser sounds to Suakin.
      Boat building and workshops in Suakin.
      Eritrean Relief Association garage in Suakin, and Mereit base area and guest house.
      Commentary on base area trip to Nacfa.
      Interview with villagers at a displaced peoples camp.
    - Tape 3, August 28 (Box 6)
      Interviews in English, Tigrinya and Tigre with people from Afabet, including commentary by Mama Zenab at Nacfa guest house.
      Battalion Office, Nacfa.
      Office in Krar, playing and singing.
      Radio from Addis.
      Tour of front line trenches and sounds of gunfire.
      Interview with female fighter.
      Concert and drinking.
      Interview at the Mosque with Dr. Andom, Agricultural Specialist.
    - Tape 4, August 29 - September 2 (Box 6)
      Trip to Orotta with an introduction to the programme.
      Interview in Himbol with Yonas, field coordinator for the Eritrean Relief Association.
      General comments.
      Zero School, English language lesson workshops, with Berkai, director of Zero School.
      Continuation of school interview with Askalu Menkerios.
      Tour of the hospital with Dr. Nerayo.
      Displaced persons camp, orphanage, and commentary on POWs.
      Truckies camp on the banks of the River Barka.
    - Tape 5, September 2-4
      Clinic at Port Sudan, with commentary on the repatriation of refugees.
      Commentary on briefing with the first secretary of the British Embassy at Khartoum.
      Tape does not include a side B.
  - 1985
    - Tape 1, July 14-17 (Box 6)
      Daily journal, Port Sudan and Orotta.
      Second Eritrean Medical Congress speeches.
      Dr. Asafa and foreign guests.
      Four songs by Red Flowers at the cultural evening.
      Commentary by Ove Engevik.
    - Tape 2, July 14-17 (Box 6)
      French TV crew, Barka River.
      Tessenai.
      Ali Ghidir irrigation plantation, Mahari.
      Work songs, Girmaica.
      Journal entry.
      Talk with displaced people from the highlands returning home.
      Interview with wounded Ethiopian captain, a POW.
      Arrival in Barentu.
      Interview with defectors from Dergue militia.
      Return to Port Sudan.
      Khartoum, journal aid workers.
  - 1990
    - Tape 1, July 30 - August 12 (Box 6)
      Side A: Travel diary from Acropole Hotel, Khartoum.
      Side B: Diary from Port Sudan, Orotta-Massawa, and Adi Keih.
    - Tape 2, August 12 (Box 6)
      Adi Keih diary.
      Sabah Fessehaie, female prisoner for three years.
      Interview with a Lutheran World Services storeman. In English.
      Interviews with Gebre Gerassus and Gerazi Wolde Sellassie, a recent defector from Asmara. In English.
    - Tape 3, August 12-13 (Box 6)
      Continued interview with Gerzai Wolde Selassie.
      Interview with Goitom Gebre Hiwet, a merchant and former prisoner of the Dergue.
      Diary.
    - Tape 4, August 13 (Box 6)
      Diary at Senafe.
      Axum ruins, church, and peasants.
      Interview with Blatta Mohamed Omer (aged 80), former Muslim League MP in Eritrean Parliament. In English and Tigrinya.
      Continuation of Blatta Mohamed Omer interview.
      Interview with Graznamach Salah Mohammed (aged 72), former Muslim League MP in Eritrean Parliament and present on November 14, 1962 when the Governor dissolved the Eritrean Parliament. In English and Tigrinya.
    - Tape 5, August 13-14 (Box 6)
      Diary in Senafe.
      Interview in Senafe with Osman, Central Committee member of Eritean People's Liberation Front.
      Interview with Graznamamch Wolde Lassus (aged 87). In English and Tigrinya.
      Continued interview with Lassus.
      Interview in Adi Keih with Capuchin Father Tessay and Gebre Abraham. In English.
      Diary in Massawa.
    - Tape 6, August 14 (Box 6)
      Side A: Interview with Issayas and Richard Leonard. In English.
      Side B: Conclusion of interview.
  - 1991
    All audio cassettes were recorded in September of 1991 but there is no specific date provided for each tape.
    - Tape 1, undated (Box 6)
      Journal in Addis Abeba.
      Diary in Asmara, Eritrea.
      Journal in Asmara, Eritrea.
    - Tape 2, undated (Box 6)
      Journal.
      Interview with Aolde ab Aoldemariam.
      Conclusion of interview.
      Untitled journal entry.
    - Tape 3, undated (Box 6)
      Untitled journal.
      Revolutionary songs.
      Visit to shoe factory.
      Wedding in Mendefera of Amdom and Nekeste.
    - Tape 4, September 21 (Box 6)
      Side A: Wedding.
      Side B: Journal in Asmara.
    - Tape 5, undated (Box 6)
      Side A: Interview with the Secretariat of the Provisional Government of Eritrea, Issayas Afwerki.
    - Tape 6, undated
  - 1993
    This set of audio cassettes contains the daily description of events during the independence referendum vote held between April 21 and 23, 1993.
    - Tape 1, April 19-21 (Box 6)
      Sides A and B: Journals from Asmara.
    - Tape 2, April 23-24 (Box 6)
    - Tape 3, April 22-23 (Box 6)
      Sides A and B: Referendum in Barentu, Gash Barka.
    - Tape 4, April 24-26 (Box 6)
    - Tape 5, April 26 (Box 6)
- Videorecordings, 1980s-1990s (Box 6)
  6 VHS cassettes and 2 DVDs.
  - San Jose, CA lecture, 2 VHS cassettes, 1999 (Box 6)
  - The Battle of Massawa in Tigrinya, 1 VHS cassette, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Fred Hallows: Man of Vision and 17 1/2 to Asmara, 1 VHS cassette, 1980s (Box 6)
  - To Asmara with Thomas Keneally, 1 VHS cassette, 1980s (Box 6)
  - CNN’s Insight, 1 VHS cassette, 1990s (Box 6)
  - Eritrea/Ethiopia in Italian, 2 DVDs, 1990s (Box 6)